But at 07:01, I'd like to call the public
meeting,
the regular public meeting of the Planning and Zoning Commission to order.
My name is Jed Larson. I am the Chairman of the Planning and Zoning Commission.
Seated
on the board
this evening
are myself,
Scott Bersaun,
Anne Cremay,
Susan England and
that is it.
So that's
the first
order of business on the agenda which is the roll call and the seating of alternates.
Moving on to the third item which is additions or changes to the agenda.
And does anybody have any additions or changes to the agenda for this evening?
I don't.
>> Okay, the one
change that I would like to make is
I think
just a
Yes,
>> Jerry. I
don't know how you want to handle this, but the first item under
the public hearing is the application for rear lots.
And our application is not rear lots
because under
the open space
requirements
they have enough frontage
that it needs not be a rear lot.
>> We
discuss
that when we get there because I was not
sure why we were applying for a rear lot either.
Okay,
good enough. I understand
>> your comment.
Only change to the agenda that
I would make is after the line where we discussed the two applications,
where it says close the public hearing, the next line should say continue the regular meeting, where we will go in and the Commission will discuss
the applications.
>> Hello, this is Leanne. Can you hear me?
I can hear you Leanne. Yep, thank you for joining. Can you see me? Can you I see can you. Nope. Okay, this is only the second time I've done this so I can see everybody else but I don't know what to do to make myself seen so as long as you can hear me and maybe Amanda can help me at some other time
so I can be seen but anyway as long as you can hear me. Okay,
very good. I was actually on before and I could hear you calling the meeting to order but
I had to call in separately, apparently. It says videoaudio,
but I needed to call in separately. It said told me for the audio. That's what I was doing.
>> Okay. Yep. Then
I will not be so bold as to try and help you from memory. I did
>> get there, but I understand that there are some tricks to it. Leanne, if you move your mouse around the screen and go to the bottom, do you see where it says start video on the bottom left hand side?
Now I lost the picture.
I'll try to help you on the side, Leanne.
>> Okay.
Okay, now I have it back.
So am I seated?
You are seated, Leanne. Yes.
Okay. Thank you.
>> Okay.
So we're on to item four on the agenda, which is public speak.
Is there anybody from the public
who would like to speak on any of the items
on any topic other than the items that are currently on the agenda for this evening?
Please raise your hand.
Any hands up there Amanda?
>> Let's see let me double check. I see one.
Liz?
>> Yeah,
I'm not I don't I'm not sure I understand the question. Anything that's not on the agenda you're asking for feedback on? Yes, there could be some members of the public who join the meeting and they want to
>> say whatever's
on their mind as opposed to when we go to the different agenda items, we'll give you the opportunity to speak directly onto that. Okay. Gotcha.
So Thank
having heard
nothing on the public speak, we will
move on to new business. And the first item is to open the public hearing,
which
I will do now. So at 07:06,
we will open the public hearing.
And
with that, Jim, would you like to
run us through
the first application?
>> First application is a special
permit
Lake
Road,
property of application
of Vincent Grimaldi.
Permit under section 4.9
rear lot and common drive.
Now I purposely,
I told Mr.
Grimaldi
that a special permit was needed and I'm standing by that.
Yes, in fact,
real it does meet the rear the application,
the dimensions meet the rear lock criteria,
but nonetheless it's a rear lock. The rear lock requires special permit. It's me it was that simple.
The rear the rear lot and the common drive
special permit
requires action prior to the subdivision application.
And the application as we know are
it's
open space
application.
The applicant is proposing
to deed over
open space, not to deed over to grant a conservation easement on a portion of the property.
Okay.
Spoken at length with, the applicant engineer,
and he's prepared to address
this matter.
I have no issues
with the application other than there were a few minor details
that were not in compliance,
but I know that Jerry Hardisty is prepared to address those and that involves actual
document for open space
to address an issue with the septic system requirements.
I believe that's it.
With that?
>> Okay, now, so we've got two different applications.
The first that we're talking about now is for two rear lots served by a common dry.
Correct. The second application
is for approval of a two lot
subdivision.
And
I think we're going with the open space
subdivision
regulations. Yes.
And so
I'm
still
curious if we have the sufficient frontage on the road
to meet a normal lot,
why need
to call it a rear lot.
And I don't think it's going to change the outcome any. I'm just
not sure I understand the thought process if
for the
lot you have to have, and I forget exactly how many feet it is for frontage for a normal
open space
subdivision
lot.
I thought the Grimaldi's lot had sufficient frontage
to make two regular lots.
>> I'm looking under interval.
Interval Lake Zone
as well as ARD rear lot.
But there's my point is they're still called rear lots.
So he does meet the requirement.
But there's still rear lots period
that that's.
Can I jump in here?
Sure. Yes, please, Jerry.
Sorry.
>> Our original application was for a conventional
subdivision.
We didn't have 200 feet of frontage,
so we applied for rear lot status.
And the rear lots allow you to shrink the frontage to 40 feet each lot,
but you have to increase the required size of the lots, which wasn't a problem because this is a big parcel.
When
we met and talked about
alternatives,
we looked at the open space requirements
and the ARD open space
frontage requirements,
if you comply with the open space design,
the frontage
requirement is only 40 feet.
And we have
much more than that,
so
so it no longer is a rear lot situation
because we comply with the frontage of an open space subdivision.
>> Okay. Now, Jerry,
this is Jed, and
one of the things I forgot to say about
the public hearing tonight is one that is recorded.
And two,
if you're going to make a comment, please announce your name so we know who it is because there are some people who
are on the phone and not
looking at everybody.
Anyhow, going back to the comment you were just addressing, Jerry, when I look at the chart
from section 11.2
space requirements,
which is what I thought you were referring,
I see an Andover Lake open space subdivision
lot
with a required minimum frontage of 50 feet.
Correct.
>> And the open space
rear lot
with a minimum requirement of 25 feet.
And so as I understand, we've got 50 feet for each of the lots for a total of 100 foot of frontage.
I did not think that we needed to have a rear lot
specified.
No,
I agree. They've
>> got two thirty feet of frontage essentially,
which is more than compliant with the open space requirement.
>> Okay so Jim I'm coming back to you to
help me understand.
>> Okay first of all,
as far as the application goes,
special permit application was still needed, the fees were the same.
It was just the difference between
requiring a special permit for both
common drive and the rear lots.
I'm sticking with my call on it's still a rear lot, period. It
meets the criteria, but it's a rear lot. And a rear lot requires
a special permit for exception for 4.9 of the zoning rates.
>> What what again, Jerry Hardisty. Jim,
what constitutes a rear lot? What's the the definition of a rear lot?
I was on the impression that a rear lot is a lot that does not have the required frontage for a standard lot.
Correct.
And it's not a standard lot.
>> So
because we have an open space subdivision,
we meet the requirements for lot frontage.
Under a rear lot?
No,
>> no. It's a Okay, if I had up and over rural design, 200 foot lot width.
>> That's under Andover Rural Design, correct. But we are using the open space
subdivision
requirement,
which is 50 feet.
>> Okay. I mean, I it's semantics to me. I mean, elsewhere in the regulations, does
perhaps you're right.
Elsewhere it's a real lot.
It's a lot that doesn't have 200 foot width.
>> Jerry, just to be clear for everybody here,
what is the frontage along the road?
It's two thirty.
>> So we About two thirty feet. I think one of them is 99 something and one of them is 131
something. So
>> if I go to our regulations
under section 4.9.2,
the definition of a rear lot
is a lot in one of the foresight zones with less than the required lot width on an accepted town road.
So my
conclusion is
that
with the frontage that we have,
we
are not discussing
a rear lot tonight.
I will accept that. That's fine. And
>> so I don't know what
the point of
order might be here, but I think
we
have met,
I know we have met the requirements
for the special permit for the driveway
for a rear lot.
And so I think it's really
a moot point and we've really got the
second of the two
applications
is what we really need to discuss tonight, which is the open space subdivision requirements.
So before
>> we
proceed to the second one,
is there anybody
in the public
that would like to speak on
behalf of the rear
lot discussion?
Hi, this is Sue and Roger Bristol.
Okay. Hi, Sue, Roger. We've
>> been following the progress of
Vinny and Pat's
project here and
we feel that they've
environmentally been meeting all of the
asks for the project and that they're acting responsibly and
doing everything they need to do.
Okay.
I
understand the comment.
So
>> I don't know if this has to do with the real life situation or whatever,
but as
abutting
neighbors
and Patty's lot,
we support this and they have gone
above and beyond what has been asked of them.
So we think this should be approved.
>> Okay.
Thank you for your input.
Anybody else
from the public that would like to make a comment on the rear lot
application?
Yeah, I
would, yes. And who's speaking? Andrew
Hoglund.
Okay, go ahead. I was wondering if I could see a site plan of the proposed design
of
what they're doing, I suppose.
Will bring up the site plans when we start talking about the second application,
which is for the Open Space subdivision.
>> Great, thanks. So we'll have a chance to go through all those. So I just wanted to point out, my name is Amanda Gibson. I'm the admin assistant for the town. All of the documents
for this
meeting, for these applications
are on the planning and zoning
site on the town website
at anniversaryt.org.
So there's some site plans as well
as some other supporting
documents.
If anyone would like to view them, I just wanted to point that out for everyone. Thank you.
>> Any other public comments? Okay,
with that,
I will close the discussion
on the first application
and we will move on to the second application,
which is for the open space subdivision.
Jim, do you want to discuss
that please? Again,
>> this is a two lot
subdivision,
23 acres approximate totals.
Originally came in as a subdivision
and after discussion with the applicant
their the applicants and their engineer,
I need to go with
the open space clustered
provision
provisions
in section 5.5 of the regulations.
With that, I guess
I would like to turn over to or I'd like to turn it back to you, Jed. Okay.
>> So
is the application
complete that we have for the Open Space Subdivision, Jim?
I believe it is, yes. Okay, very good.
>> Jerry, would you be willing to walk us through that application?
I would be willing to try.
We'll see how
>> inept I am at sharing my screen. That's why I'm asking you to do it rather than me.
>> Nice move. Okay
I'm gonna hit share screen and I think that
my stuff will come up here.
Okay
can people see this?
I can stay at good yes.
>> Okay. So this is the location map.
The Grimaldi's have a nice piece of property on the East Elbow of Andover Lake. It's about 22 acres.
It's on the hillside. Everything slopes down to the lake, which makes sense.
This was initially
submitted,
as Jim said, as a conventional subdivision,
the whole thing of which you should be able to see in just a minute.
So
as I said, 22 acres.
Their existing house,
nice house, is up on the hillside
overlooking this area, looking to the excuse me, looking to the west.
And
the Grimaldis want to downsize
like a lot of us,
and they have a lot of acreage here
and they wanted to
build a new house to the north of the existing house.
But they didn't want to sell all of this property with the existing house.
So in order to keep that we had to keep it contiguous
with the newly formed lot.
And that's why we have this strip of land that goes behind
the main house the original house.
So the stuff to the right on this
drawing and the stuff to the left on this drawing is connected and is all one parcel.
You
can see that we have the
existing house is going to go with about four acres,
and the remaining land is about 18 acres.
When we met with Jim and Eric and Jeb and talked about options
for this,
we
realized it was better to go to an open space subdivision,
so we
did that.
And that plan is here.
The
only thing that changes about this is that the Grimaldi's will put a conservation easement over this segment of land that's highlighted in green here,
and this is about nine acres because
they have to turn over
what is it, 8% of the land,
4% of 40% of the 40% of
the land has to go to open space.
That land also can't have more than 30% wetlands.
This
is going to have a little less than two
acres of wetlands, and it has no slopes in excess of 25%,
so it meets the open space
criteria.
Everything
else remains the same as what was with the conventional subdivision.
>> Jerry, can I ask you what
made
you or the Grimaldi's
decide that the open space was preferable
to the
standard subdivision?
And if it's none of my business, I understand that too. I'm just trying to, for my own knowledge,
is the first time we've gone through one of the open space subdivisions
and it wasn't clear to me
that this turning over 40% of the land is advantageous to the Grimaldi?
>> Well, turning over
you
have one of two options. You either have to
present open space or you have to pay a fee in lieu of.
Now the open space
in in this instance and Vinny and Pat jump in if you wanna correct me on anything.
But they had no intention of developing this land anyway. It's really nice land out there. Yes. It is. And since they have no
no reason to develop it or no desire to develop it, it it made sense to make it open space.
Okay.
>> Okay.
And
I guess it avoids the issue of having to
designate it a rear lock.
>> Yes.
Yes. Obviously, the development part
gets a little bit easier in this case. Yes. Okay.
Sorry
for the interruption.
>> And Jerry.
Yes, sir? Why did you pick
that space on the South Side of the property
down by that granite monument on the town line?
Why did you just, why right there, what was the, I mean,
follow the green line to the
Columbia boundary?
Line Why that spot right there
>> where it's nine acres. It because it's just nine acres right there? Yeah, because it was convenient. There's a monument here, there's a pin down here, so it's easy to define the line. It
fits the requirement. We needed 8.8
acres and nine is pretty close to that. So
it could be defined pretty easy and
would save time and effort with that.
>> Also Is there a monument at the excuse me. This is Scott Personigan.
Yep. Is there is there a monument at at at the end of that green line or is there a monument to the Southeast?
>> The monument is a 100 feet from that line. Alright.
But it gives us something that we can find in the field.
>> Not just to say if you put it at the monument, wouldn't have to change anything.
>> Well,
that's true. Except for I think that just makes us a little less than what's required.
Oh yeah.
>> That is a beautiful piece of land to put in conservation.
So
go ahead and continue, Jerry.
>> Okay.
So
this is
where they wanted their house. They've been planning on putting it here for a long time. So that's what we did.
So the next step was to design a septic system and the house layout, etcetera,
which is
shown on another sheet,
which I'm going to pop to right here.
So we did the development of this. Actually, did put the cart before the horse in this case and did the testing out here before this.
Eastern Highlands Health District was there for the test pits.
All the test pits were were pretty consistent.
It's it's
it's decent as it's as good of materials as you get in Andover, which is always a little bit problematic.
But
we tried to make this as small an area of disturbance as possible. We kept the septic systems away from the
wetlands
by more than 50 feet, which is the health code requirement.
The
main driveway, the main part of the driveway across the wetlands has already been accomplished,
so the
driveway up to the house will be done at the time of the house construction, obviously.
So this is our
septic system design sheet.
And then we added a
erosion control measures
sheet, which is a requirement of the subdivision regulations.
This spells out the
plan of attack for this thing, the sequence
of construction,
time dates, etcetera, the responsible person for the
maintenance of the plan and checking the silt fences, etcetera.
We've got a proposed topsoil stockpile area here.
We've got a settling pool designed below that so that the fines, if anything washes down here, it'll settle out here. And of course, the silt fence is already in.
So
I believe that this erosion and sediment control plan
complies with the subdivision regulations
and
fits
the design also. Mean, this is where the house should be. It's where it best fits, and
that's what we got.
>> Okay. Did you have anything else, Jerry, that you wanted to say about the three maps that you put up for us?
>> I would be happy to answer any questions that anybody has.
>> Before we get to the other questions,
I would like to
make sure that
however we do that, Amanda or Jim, that these three maps are part of the public record that we have that we make our decision on.
And then Jerry, I know you've got several other documents
that I think
are part of the public record and I don't know if
you can call those up or if I need to have Amanda do that but
I know
there's,
you know, we've got,
I'm not sure if you've got your comment from the fire marshal, you've got a letter from the neighbor, any other supporting documents that you have that you would like to have entered into the record before we get on to further questions?
>> I
was under the impression they were already in the record because I saw them in the list of things at this meeting. I don't have them on this computer,
>> unfortunately. Okay. Would you like me to get them up on the screen? I would just like to show them so I can make sure that if some people did not get a chance to go to the website and take a look at them, that they've all had a chance to see the information that's in the public record. Okay.
>> Jerry, I'm going to stop your sharing.
Just give me one second.
Okay.
Can everyone see my screen?
>> No.
Not yet. Looks like it's headed that way. Here we go. Yep. Okay.
>> So just let me know which document you'd like to see. Okay. Let's start
>> with the statement of intent. We'll just work our way
down.
Everyone
may have to tilt their head.
>> Okay.
Well, it's not
a very long letter.
Okay, got that.
If you could go to the next one please.
I'll see what it says.
Nope.
Do you like this?
Letter of support.
>> Of support for the St. James.
Oh. But whatever one comes up, we'll take a look at it. I've got my list that I'm expecting to see.
Okay.
Got it. Amanda, if you can go to the next one then. And if anybody
needs more time to take a look at the documents as we're scrolling through them, just
let me know.
>> And just for the record, Linda McDonald is on the meeting tonight. She's clerking the meeting. I am just here for some
moral and technical support.
>> And I appreciate that.
K. And for the record then, this is the letter from the St. James who are
the neighbors of the Grimaldi's there.
Okay, thank you Amanda.
Like to see the Eastern Highlands approval?
>> Yep, that's good.
Okay, so this letter provides the approval for the septic system and the private
well.
Okay, thank you Amanda.
Looking for the inland wetlands summary ruling.
And if you can scroll
down a little bit on that, Amanda. This is going take a little time because I have not seen this document
prior to now. So if you can go back up where
yep, hold on. That's good. Hold on there for just a minute.
Okay,
>> yep, scroll down to the top of page two.
Okay, so it looks like by this letter we have the approval
to install the 18 inches culvert,
fill approximately
nineteen
sixty square feet of wetlands
and disturbance
by grading and filling of 0.45
acres of the Upland Review Area.
House well
and septic inside the Upland Review Area. Okay, if you can scroll down from there Amanda, please.
Okay and I know the Grimaldi's
are anxious to get started on this so we do have a typo
in paragraph four.
We've got five brackets two years for the duration of the permit.
I don't know which of those two numbers was intended. My expectation is that probably you would be done,
you would hope to be done within two years.
>> The
standard approval length is five years.
I will tell you that.
>> Okay.
And I'm fine with that. I didn't I know Grimaldi's are anxious to get started.
Okay, if you could scroll down to the top of the next page, Amanda.
Okay. Is there anything below that?
Okay, I'm ready for you to scroll down just a little bit more.
Okay. I'm all set. Is there anything else or are we done there?
Okay.
So now
you turn it back over to Jerry, we'll go back to the maps and
we will entertain questions from the public.
Unless there was anything else you wanted to add, Jerry?
No, I'm good.
>> Mr. Mizgrimaldi,
anything you would like to add before we get back into asking
questions on the application?
You have anything you want to add?
>> Nope. Just to
reiterate what you said Jed, just want to get this moving.
You know how long we've been working on this.
We're coming on a year's time.
And I'm just about to blow my patience.
And I will add that in all this
to find out
a week ago
And because of the COVID nineteen,
now the banks aren't even looking at construction loans.
So this year long process to get us to this point
has been agonizing.
So anybody
on this call,
I plead to every one of you, anything that you can do so we can be proved and
move on with our life and not have to worry about this ever again.
Please help us.
I'm going to put the SOS out out there.
Thanks to Liz and Ed and Jerry and
Roger or I'm sorry.
Sue and Roger. Our
neighbors next door that wrote the nice letter, Chris and Chrissy,
And all the other abutters to this property.
I think some of some of what you're doing is you're you're making a mole of,
you know,
a mountain out of a molehill.
Let's just get to the verb and get it done with.
>> Okay.
Did anybody in the public have any questions on the application at this point?
>> I'm going to unmute.
Please speak up if you would like.
Andrew?
I'm good no no I just want to
>> say Ed and I want to say you know in furtherance of our approval
this just helps the town,
okay? This is an additional
tax revenue for the town.
Not to mention all the other issues that the Grimaldi's
have had to go through to get this approved so
let's get it done. Okay?
>> I understand the comment.
Hearing no other questions from the public,
do any of the commission members
have any questions?
I hear no questions from the commission members.
We commenting on the plan.
Yes, Scott.
>> Are are the septic requirements in the ARD the same as
subdivision
septic requirements,
Jerry?
Yep.
There's no mention of them in the ARD
section.
>> Distance to wetlands and the rest of it all 50?
Well, that's what the state health code is.
>> You didn't find anything in the ARD
to specify that
nothing in the ARD
Jed, do you know anything about that?
>> I don't.
What I do know
in the
point that I had a bit of a concern about is that
in the subdivision regulations
under the sanitary
authorization,
it talks about
doing the test pits
between February and May. And I know from the map they were done in August.
And that's why I wanted to make sure we got the
letter
from Eastern Highlands Health District
because that's
their purview.
If they say
that they're satisfied with it,
I was not going to take any issue.
To
the contrary,
that's that's their area of expertise and that's theirs to decide.
Okay. We've
>> had that. So what are we what are we doing here? What are we talking about?
We've got we've had the letter. It's been in the file.
>> I understand. And and we're just
making sure that
the questions
that we have are answered.
I agree that you've got the letter in your file.
It's a non issue. The Eastern Highlands Health District has approved your plan.
>> I have to say something, you know, from the town's end of this, you know,
this
may have seemed like it took a long time and it probably did take a long time and, you know, the town apologizes for everything that went on, but there's reasons
we this didn't get
it didn't take so long because of no reason there was no the biggest reason was you know our zoning enforcement agent
left he retired
and your frustration
is you know warranted but
there's there's reasons for everything that happened here.
This is the first time that the Planning and Zoning Commission has seen
any
real information on this plan
so
everybody being up in arms about
how long this has taken
really needs to take a breath.
We don't have any problem with any of the things that we've seen here just
just take a breath this will all come through
and now we have this COVID thing we still don't have a zoning agent
you know the one that we had left now we have
Jim
and he's doing the best that he can to get everything together. We understand that, Scott.
We understand it. I I I don't, you know, we're we're trying to get this done.
We really are.
Just want you to understand our side.
>> The
question I had is
in the area
that's cleared
in support of
putting the house in,
was any clearing done through the wetlands themselves
just because as I look up the hill it looks fairly open?
I know you were given authorization
by John Valenti
to disrupt
0.54
acres, think it was, in the Upland Review area.
I'm just trying to
satisfy
myself that
we did not
go in and clear through the wetlands themselves.
>> Jed, the wetlands that was cleared was exactly what was proposed and approved by
Inland Wetlands. And this whole area, if you
drew along the outline of the where
the silt fence is proposed and the edge of the tree line comes out to 0.45
acres.
That number wasn't arbitrary.
Produced it based on the drawings that we had.
Okay.
>> Very good. All right. Can I make a comment here, please? Vincent Cromalvy.
You remember me, the applicant. Right? Right. Right. Alright. If you take a look at the maps, all three of them, the wetlands are clearly delineated on the maps.
Alright? I'll be happy to describe it for you.
The only disturbance we did was putting the driveway through the wetlands. Of course, we had to disturb the wetlands to get the driveway through. Had approval of that back in July
2019.
Where that house is situated, there's no wetlands cutting through that house or where it was cleared.
Alright? This has been
since July
2019.
You know, and
as far as Scott's comment about
not seeing anything on this, I have no idea what you're talking about. I applied to planning and zoning in September
2019.
This planning and zoning commission discussed this project in September
2019,
then they discussed it again in December
then they discussed it again in February
2020,
then this commission discussed it again in March 2020,
and here we are in April discussing it again. You guys tell me it's the first time you've seen anything?
>> Extremely frustrating. Okay. So, mister Grimaldi,
just just for the record,
I think several of those meetings you're talking about are with the Inland Wetlands Commission. Exactly. Did you not just say what I said, sir?
>> Check your minutes. Planning and Zoning Commission discussed this five times already. Go back to the minutes and read the minutes. We're all over in you've documented our names multiple times in the minutes. We've had multiple discussions.
Planning is
>> Let's get back to can we get back to questions on the drawing itself so we can finish this,
Please.
>> Okay. Any other questions on the drawings?
Jim, did you have any comments to make?
No.
>> Okay. And
I'll go back to Jerry for any concluding comments before we bring the public hearing to a close.
>> Well,
I will tell you that when we were
talking about
the possibility of an open space
subdivision as opposed to the conventional, I think it turned out for the best for Rimaldi's
and the town for that matter. And I think that this is an
appropriate and a good use of the land and a good application of the open space subdivision.
That's all I got. Okay.
>> Mr. And Ms. Rimaldi,
any closing comments?
Or do I take it that your previous comments were your closing comments?
Do you have any closing comments?
I don't know where we are in this meeting.
>> Jerry, just We are we are I've heard yeah. I've heard that. Public hearing.
>> One one thing I would like to say because this has been going on for almost a year now,
we've experienced some financial hardships because of this.
Because
we were told we were approved back in July 2019 by the zoning agent
that all it had to do was have a
administrative
approval,
which never happened.
So
because of that, we moved forward with the bank. We've lost hundreds of dollars with the bank.
My contract my excavation contract, his machine's been sitting there all winter. I don't even know what that's gonna cost me yet.
So this committee's
inability
to act on this has caused us much hardship.
I'd like you to take that into consideration,
please. Okay.
>> Understand, and I will provide the following feedback on that,
is that
when
there was an understanding
that there would be an administrative review to
approve building the house,
it was not recognized
that this was an already
subdivided
lot.
We thought that this would be the first cut which would take no Planning and Zoning Commission approval at all.
It turned out that when we look back at the deed,
that it had already been subdivided
once in the past since the subdivision records went into effect.
And that is why you had to bring
an application before the Commission.
It's unfortunate
the timing that
required that,
but that is the
reason
that we had to come to the Planning and Zoning Commission
after you initially thought that that would not be required.
Okay.
And with that,
we will close the public meeting at
well,
one other thing before I close the meeting. And Jerry, I was interested
in
where we stand with the draft open space conveyance instrument
that's required to be submitted as part of the application?
>> I
would like
to have that a condition of approval and allow them to work on that afterwards,
because obviously
if this thing doesn't go through, then they're not going to waste the money on having that drafted.
I believe we've done that in the past on previous
applications.
So that
will Yes,
Jim.
>> I'd be happy to speak to that if the commission so wishes.
Please do.
In about
round twenty ten, there was a subdivision
off of
Long Hill Road and
it involved a conservation easement.
It was in fact
a condition of approval that that the
the document
language
of the conservation,
the de restrictions
be approved
prior
to
issuance of
occupancy,
certificate
of occupancy.
Would it allow
the developer to move forward.
>> Okay, so my
question before we close the public hearing to Mr. Mizravaldi
is it your intention that the open space be left in the pristine condition that it is today?
Yes, it is. Okay,
>> thank you.
And with that, at
07:55,
we will close
the public hearing.
The next order of business
is to open,
reopen the regular meeting.
And so we will recall the regular meeting to order is 07:56.
I was looking for my copy of the agenda here and I know
the next item on the agenda
is to discuss
the first
application,
which was a special permit
for two rear lots served by a common drive in accordance with section 4.9 of the town of Andover zoning regulations.
Does anybody
on the commission
have any comments that they would like to make regarding
that application?
Okay,
hearing no comments.
And based on our discussion
that we had in the public hearing,
It seems as if the requirement
for a rear lot
did not exist
and therefore this application
is unnecessary.
And
I would like to have a motion from one of the Commission members
that
the application
for rear lot
is not necessary
and will allow the Commission
an opportunity to vote on that.
>> I'll make a motion
to
get rid of the
application
for
the two rear lots.
Vincent Grimaldi,
353 Lake Road.
Special permit for two rear lots,
Common Drive,
accordance with Section 4.9 of Landor
zoning regulations.
Anybody,
I'm looking for a second.
Second.
And who was that? Ann. Ann,
second.
Any discussion
>> on that motion?
Susan England here.
Would we like to modify
the
motion to indicate that the reason
why it's not necessary
is because the two lots have adequate frontage and do not meet the definition of being a rear lot?
So moved.
Okay.
Any other discussion?
>> Yeah, is Jim Nalzi, can I chime in? Go ahead Jim. If
the Commission
acts on that motion
presented,
you eliminate the common drive
and you couldn't approve the subdivision without the common drive.
Also, I just want to point out that it was the same application.
The common drive and the rear lots were part of the same application. It didn't
make the Grimaldi's go through
a lot of extra work on that.
I understand.
Okay. But
if you want,
>> you wanna act on the, wanna remove the rear lot, I mean that makes sense,
but if you remove the common,
you don't approve common drive,
then you don't have a valid subdivision in my opinion.
So we we have to redo that.
>> Okay.
A question for you, Jim. And I am looking at our subdivision regulations,
Article 7.7,
item 12,
which states common driveways
may be allowed
provided the driveway serves no more than two dwellings.
And so as I read through the subdivision regulations,
I thought that what the Grimaldis were
looking to do
was
per our subdivision regulations.
>> It is.
But we also have zoning regulations.
If you look at section 4.9,
it states
that
deals with driveways.
Commission may grant special permits proving the construction of common driveways
to a maximum of two adjacent rear lots.
>> I
understand, but this piece of property does not meet the requirement
of a rear lot.
And so
we don't need
to get into the rear lot regulations.
>> Regulations
don't distinguish between
they talk about common driveways.
All right, I mean that's the way you read it.
But we've got you need a special need
an easement on a common drive.
That's the way the regulations were written.
I
did I did notice that they talked about we're lost, but I still think anybody went back and revisited
this section of the regulations when the when the open space subdivision
component was written.
If
>> you don't if you don't grant a special permit
and you don't have any conditions,
then you have a common drive,
no maintenance,
no provisions for maintenance,
no sharing of costs.
Mean, it's a common drive
requires
an easement period.
Easement shown on the drawing, Jim.
>> And the document The easement's on the drawing. What's that gonna do for the for a buyer?
Excuse me? I mean, an easement is a document filed in the land records. Right.
Okay. Well
It doesn't do anything on the drawing.
Especially people what they want. I mean,
I don't understand it.
>> So as I was preparing for this meeting, I looked at three different places
to find driveway requirements.
One was in section 4.16
of our regulations,
which is
just basic driveway
requirements.
Then I looked at the rear lot driveway requirements
and then I looked at the subdivision
driveway requirements.
And I do recognize your comment that
there needs to be some understanding of who is going to plow the driveway
and I can't put my finger on exactly where those words are in there right this minute,
I do think that our regulations
do not preclude
the common driveway going to two lots that we're trying to to do.
But that should be in
the
motion
so that the commission members can vote on that and that's not just me
making that decision.
So
I guess I would like to ask Jerry or Mr. And Ms. Grimaldi,
what were the plans
if you eventually sell the house
that exists there now
for maintenance of the common section of the driveway?
>> There's gonna be a shared cost between both owners on the common portion of the driveway.
Was discussed when the plans were drawn up.
>> Okay, thank you.
So
is there any other discussion on the first
application?
And I'd like to go back, somebody brought
up a good point that the reason
that we're not
requiring
this application
is because of the sufficient common frontage.
I'm not sure
that
since the
application
doesn't discuss driveways we need to add these
maintenance
rules to that
discussion.
Think we just say
that we have met the requirement for standard
subdivision,
standard open space subdivision
frontage,
and so the application was required.
So at this point,
we had
a motion,
we had it seconded,
we had an amendment to the motion
to add the words that it was not required because of adequate frontage.
And I'm looking for a second to the motion
amendment. I'll
second that too, Ms. Ann.
>> Okay,
thank you, Ann.
So
at this point, we are going to vote on the amendment
to the motion.
And so,
Anne, how do you vote?
Or
approve.
Scott?
Aye.
Leanne?
And I vote aye. Oh,
and I vote aye also.
Okay,
>> thank you, Susan.
So the motion carries five-zero.
Now we're going to vote on the amended
motion in its
entirety.
That is
the elimination
of the application because it had sufficient frontage.
Anne, how do you vote on that? Aye.
Scott? Aye.
>> Leanne?
Aye.
Susan?
Aye. And I vote aye as well.
The
motion passes
five-zero
that the application
for the rear lots is not required.
Moving on to the second
application.
For approval of a two lot subdivision in accordance with Andover subdivision regulations in section 5.5
of Andover
zoning regulations,
which is the open space subdivision.
Jim, do you have a proposed motion
drafted for that article?
I do.
>> Is it possible that we can call that up on the screen so that we can take a look at it?
Yes.
Amanda, do you have that?
Or Linda?
Give me a minute. Sure.
Okay.
Okay, direct me on where to scroll here.
>> Well I'm not seeing
a motion, just see
please find the attached draft motion.
>> Okay, hold on one second. Let me try again. Okay.
Oh, I see.
Can you see it now?
>> It's working on it.
There
we go. Okay.
Okay. If you scroll down on that a little bit, Amanda.
>> I'm not sure the
draft motion actually calls for filing of the
covenants in the open space.
I
>> see that. I'm
not positive.
Is
there anything below this, Amanda, if you scroll down more? Is six at the end?
Okay.
With Jim,
it looks to me like
item three
would be scratched because and
then scroll up a little bit more, Amanda.
I'd like to
the driveway easement.
There's got to be language for that.
>> Okay, go ahead and scroll up
again some more there.
Okay,
>> so
I am under the impression that we would scratch the first paragraph
because that
let's see.
Yeah,
>> the first section
discusses the rear lots
and should be eliminated.
The second section
looks good and then
there's the one section on the conditions.
I think it was paragraph three down below.
Yes.
>> Okay, so I'm looking for somebody to make a motion
based on the second paragraph up for the lead in in all the conditions
with the exception of number three. Is
>> there anything else?
Can can we speak about anything else? What when did the pin get put on this?
>> When did the Below pin that. Scott number four.
And again, if there are extra conditions that we need to, this is just a draft
that
Jim prepared
for the eventuality that we got this far. If there are other conditions that anybody would like to see included in this, now's the time to discuss those.
>> Jerry who who just as well as we can take away. Jerry who is the person that's responsible for finding the
the pinther put in there?
I'm sorry. Who's responsible for It says building inspector responsible for that because he's the one that's gonna give the CEO a right?
>> No. The zoning enforcement officer typically
is the one that checks something like that but honestly they
they typically ask for a letter from the surveyor saying that all the pins have been put in. Okay and you're gonna put that in there?
If I'm the surveyor.
>> Think the prints that you did, Jerry, look very nice. Thank you.
Thank you.
Any other comments, Scott, pertaining to the monumentation?
>> No, because I've seen other
things that we've done along the way and nobody ever put the pins in.
>> Okay.
I'm
sure Jim will make sure that we get those there.
So I'm looking for
somebody to make a motion for the approval
of the
application for Open Space Subdivision.
Mr. Chairman, this is Linda, your clerk.
Yes, Linda.
Someone has to read the entire record.
>> Should something be added? Should something be added to number four who's responsible for that?
Shouldn't shouldn't just be open. It's too open.
>> You you Scott, it says before the CEO, so that should be a CEO
standard.
>> Should be.
Just Jim Hellenstein, what I I do is required on the.
Typically,
plans
show
proposed monumentation
and it's up to the engineer to modify the language on that to say install,
as far as I'm concerned.
But again, you're right, Gary's right, it is the CEO responsibility.
But that's how I
>> So I would expect that Jim, you would be making sure the monumentations
installed
prior to the issuance of the certificate of occupancy.
Yes.
Okay.
>> That's how I do it as opposed to going out and
field check them because it's just not practical.
>> I'm not smart enough to know how the
actual gets done. I just want to make sure that you as the zoning officer
satisfy
yourself that we've got the monumentation installed.
And so you're going to do that, Jim? Yes. Okay, thank you.
I can't remember if we had somebody that made a motion.
Is anybody willing to do that?
When you will, you will end up having to read it. Somebody has to read this whole thing.
Scott, was that you making a motion?
>> I
guess I need to be able to read the whole document.
>> Well, it's not very long.
I know. I've been a lot longer.
I'm not in charge of that, cursor.
>> Okay, yep. I just tried moving it myself and
did not.
Anyhow, is there a second to the motion?
And Scott will read the entire motion
as soon as we get a second for it.
That was Anne?
Leanne.
>> Leanne. Okay, thank you Leanne.
So
Amanda, if you can roll up to the top here,
Scott will read the motion into the record.
>> Amanda you're gonna have to move it as I read it okay?
I got you Scott.
>> All right I move to approve the application of Minsinkramaldi
353 Lake Road Andover
application for two
lot open space cluster subdivision in accordance with section 5.5
of the Andover zoning regulations
and Andover subdivision regulations
in their entirety.
As shown on a plan entitled open space Subdivision Plan,
Grimaldi Subdivision
Lake Road, Andover, Connecticut prepared by Civil Engineering Services
LLC
dated oneseventeentwenty
twenty with the following conditions:
open space covenants.
Amanda.
Number
one, the applicant shall provide planning and zoning commission with a document detailing the proposed
open space covenant
subject to approval by the town attorney and the planning and zoning Commission prior to the issuance of any certificate
of occupancy
number two driveway easement.
The applicant shall provide the town with documents detailing the proposed language for the requisite driveway easement and shall be subject to review and approval by the town attorney.
Special permit required for the rear lots and common drive shall be filed by the applicant along with the final mileage.
Scott, we're not taking that
>> That's the paragraph that we're eliminating Scott. We're taking that one out? Yes. Okay, I'm gonna strike number three.
Okay, number three monumentation,
all monumentation depicted on the plans installed prior to the issuance of a certificate of occupancy.
Number five signing of mylars,
Mylar plan shall be endorsed by the chairman of the planning and zoning commission prior to filing. And number six,
filing costs. This is expressly understood that all costs associated with the aforementioned
filing requirements shall be borne by the applicant.
You need a second. Okay,
>> that is the motion. It's in the record.
Any further discussion on the motion?
Hearing none, we'll call for a vote.
Anne?
Aye.
Scott?
Leanne?
Aye.
>> Susan?
And I vote aye as well. The motion passes
five-zero-zero.
Thank you everybody. I know it was hard getting to this point and
I appreciate everybody's patience.
With that we will move on to
the next item of new business
which is
the subdivision
pre application review for 26 Old Farms Road.
Is there somebody
present that
wishes to speak to that application?
>> Yes, my name is George Correa.
And
what
myself, my family and my sister and her family are looking to do is to purchase this 13.94
acre piece of land
there in Andover
and divide it into two lots
and basically build, you know,
two houses.
>> Okay.
And
we
did get your
preliminary discussion,
but I did not see the drawing that your preliminary
discussion referenced.
Do you mind if we share our screen to
That
show
would be fine. Yep.
>> Okay. So, what what you're looking at there
is
outlined in red
to the left side of the page
is
the 13.94
acre parcel.
>> I'm not sure that I see. Oh, okay. I do see.
Yeah, I've got the red now. Okay, thank you. Yep.
>> And so this particular
parcel of land is
unique in that
it has road frontage
on Pine Ridge Drive,
but it's actually accessed
from
Old Farms Road
through a
shared driveway
that
will lead in access into
the lot.
>> Do you know why it's accessed that way? That seems
>> strange to me. I do not. This is the way that
when it was originally subdivided
back in the late 80s.
This is how it was
done.
Okay.
Yeah,
>> I do not know the reasoning why it was done this way.
>> But the area outlined in red is the property that you're talking about. Yes. Okay.
Go ahead.
>> Yes. So what this what this drawing here is, is a conceptual idea that we had,
and
it's not to scale.
But this is just a rough idea of what we were thinking about doing.
So at some point
between 2000
and
and 2004,
the previous or the current owner
was able to get a
was able to get a buildable area approved,
which is highlighted in orange right there that
is being circled.
So that's a buildable an approved buildable area.
What we would like to do is we would roughly divide it in half right about here.
Okay.
>> And we would add a second buildable area
in the southwest corner
of the lot.
There in,
in the green hashed areas.
Those are wetlands
that have been delineated
during
the
original
subdivision or during the original
when this was originally
or this
building?
>> Oh yeah, when that building was approved. Yes, a buildable area was approved.
>> Do you know if those wetlands were delineated by a soil scientist?
>> Yes, they were. Okay.
So
there's two,
have two options into entering
the lot.
Option one would be to have a
three way
shared
driveway,
which would
come in from Old Farms Road
or
we could keep the
two way shared driveway coming from Old Farms Road and come in to access the rear lot
through Pine Rich Drive.
>> Okay. Anything
else?
Yeah, anything else you have at this point?
No, that's pretty much it in a nutshell.
>> Okay. Now, Jim, I know you had
some concerns
about
the plan
in
>> Yeah,
George spent
terrible amount of time researching this to his credit.
And every
option we seem to look at,
there seemed to be
obstacle.
My recollection
is that there was an intermittent stream.
I don't know whether it's
the extension of this wetland
along the property line.
I thought the stream itself was
further, further back, but nonetheless.
Assume the reason that
Pine Ridge Drive wasn't utilized
in the subdivision, which was approved back in the eighties, mid eighties as I think Woodlands 2 was the name of it. Right. You're right, As
a requirement
was the wetlands, was the stream, the stream crossing.
There's
>> an intermittent stream that crosses that he's that.
Easement or I don't know if it's an easement right away, right right away or whatever from Pine Ridge Drive
crosses and goes down to a bigger brook that comes down
to the,
south.
And then that that brook, there's a, I don't know if it's a perennial stream, but it's close to a perennial stream down here. It's intermittent goes into a almost a perennial when it goes to the hop right down here.
So crosses that that blue line there.
No subsequent,
I mean up a number of things arose,
>> a number of issues arose
during
the review. That was, I mean the number of driveways,
the number of homes served
by a common drive.
It's both in the subdivision and zoning regulations
limiting
a driveway to two dwellings
short of a waiver on the part waiver of the subdivision regs
and a variance of the zoning regs.
In addition,
subsequent to the to
the
approval of this subdivision, I'm talking Woodlands Woodlands,
I believe the Planning and Zoning Commission adopted a maximum number of homes served on a cul de sac, cul de sac being Pine Ridge.
And to add another home,
utilize that right away, land.
I'm staying away from the term rear lot here.
>> Well, think in this would add real lot is exactly the right term
>> because there is Except it's an open space subdivision, I don't know. Okay. Whatever.
It it would be too many homes on that street.
Cul de sac starts at
Pendy Road.
>> Now it it would seem inconceivable
to me, Jim, that they would put this
driveway off of Pine Ridge Drive
and not expect somebody to build on that lot back there. Now is the question building one house versus two?
Or do you think that
the number of houses would be exceeded on the cul de sac by just putting one house on the property?
>> Well,
at the time it was approved, the time Woodlands was approved, there was no cap.
Okay.
>> And mean, it only comes into play if the house is served off of Pine Ridge Drive.
If there's frontage on Pine Ridge, but it's not served by,
it doesn't, it's not utilized.
That piece of land is not utilized as a driveway for access or some
other way to get there from Pine Ridge Drive
that wouldn't be counted
against that cap,
the number.
What section of the
and and what regulation that
>> would I believe it's somewhere in this in the subdivision regs.
>> And I am not familiar with that.
I got heavily involved in the subdivision regs with respect to the last issue.
There's enough regs there that I'm not familiar with all of them. I don't know offhand. I mean, haven't
reviewed the plan because
there's no application.
>> Okay, no.
And certainly one of the things that
I would like to do better than we did on the last application
is to have a complete application
in place before
we go to a public hearing so that the commission
can
have a good understanding
of
what it is that you're asking to do there. And
so
Jim with the wetlands on there,
I'm assuming that this would need a review through the wetlands commission before it comes to us.
>> Yes, it would. Okay.
George, let me, I don't mean to speak for you, but I think quite
frankly, the applicant just wanted to get a feel for
what, how the commission might
view it, what issues there were before he moved forward,
incur a lot of expense which is certainly
understandable.
>> Well I know in the letter,
I think it's this one that
it says that
time is an important factor.
And I'm not sure what those time constraints are,
but I do know that
by the time
an application comes to planning and zoning,
we have to wait fourteen days to see if anybody
in the public objects to the application.
Then we schedule, we have sixty five days to schedule a public hearing.
We've got thirty days, I think, to conclude the public hearing.
Then we've got another sixty five days to act on it.
And that's been extended by an additional ninety days because of the coronavirus
crisis making
virtual meetings more cumbersome to do
than
if we were all to be able to sit down together and look at the documents and work our way through them.
So as I was
talking to Jim about this
idea
earlier today,
I think you might be able to get through all those issues.
I don't think that it's going to be quick.
And I don't think that it's going to be without cost
to you. And so that's a decision
you guys would have to make
wanting
>> to Yes, and I totally
understand where you're going with all that. And
real reason why we wanted to talk to you guys first is if this is to
confirm that this idea is feasible. If it is, then we're going to move forward in purchasing the land.
But if this is something that's going to have too many roadblocks and something that cannot be done,
then we will not, we will stop our
moving forward and purchasing the land and we will look for something else essentially.
>> My
recommendation,
and
I'm open to second guessing by any of the commission members or Jim, would be
the next step, if I were you, that I would do is I would take the same presentation to the Inland Wetlands Commission
because I think probably
the more significant
issue to get through
is the wetlands proximity
to where you're building there. But I have not been out to the property to take a look at it or anything.
I think the wetlands might be
the tougher
leg of the journey.
Do you agree with that Jim or is that off the mark?
Oh, you're probably right.
>> Don't know if the building areas are going to fit inside the wetlands there.
They're outside the wetlands. Outside the wetlands, yeah. Oh,
>> just keep in mind Scott that this is not the scale this is just something that we just drew up.
>> Right and
the wetlands would probably have to be delineated again.
And my first thing right off the bat is
why was
two houses not put in there
in the 80s when that was subdivided?
You know if a
developer
could have put two houses in there he would have put two houses in there. I'm certain of that. I know the developers that did that.
>> Yeah, well, you look at Lot 1 and Lot 2, they're comparable sizes
and it's the same.
It's just one house
on each one of those lots.
So
>> I guess that reinforces
Scott's comment that
if those
lots are
about the same size as yours,
why didn't,
well,
the developer probably would have put two houses in there if he could. He just, for
some reason, and I don't know what it is, maybe,
>> thought he couldn't. What is the what's the width of the driveway down there
off of Pine Ridge?
It's
71.34
>> feet. Could you put that print back up on there?
Amanda?
You're measuring it
at an angle, you measured it across, what did it?
>> I can only
say what's written on the drawing.
The drawing says 71.34
feet.
>> That's at a, you know, 45 degree angle or something.
And imagine
why there would be there would not be
a house in there if there could have been a house put in there.
>> Well, from what we gather about the history of this property, it was inside the current owners.
The property has been in their family, I think, for a while.
>> So I'm not sure. Yeah. Twenty five or thirty years, I think, because I yeah.
A long time.
And he never put a house in there.
>> They started construction
on that first house there, that first buildable area.
They got some of the road in place,
and then they got their erosion and sediment control in place.
But then for whatever reason, the construction stopped. Right,
>> very steep going down into that first house lot there.
The driveway
isn't going into here.
>> Well, guess then,
you know, I love the concept of two families being close together on a piece of property like that. But
Jim, would it be feasible for you to,
now that we've gotten through the last
application and
looking ahead,
can you go through and
see if you can get clarification
on will the driveway
off of Pine Ridge Drive
by our regulation support
two houses back there?
And with the number of houses be consistent
with
with the
current subdivision regs for for cul de sac loading?
Sure, can double check that.
Hey
>> Jed, just to be clear, if if we were to come in from Pine Ridge, it would only service one house.
That would be the house closest to Pine Ridge.
The
house that's,
you know,
closer to Old Farms would stay that way. So we would access from both sides.
>> Is there a reason that you wouldn't want to take both houses access from the Pine Ridge side if you could?
Perhaps
it's too steep
going up that hill.
>> Yeah, right there. Well,
I think the regulation
is
we cannot exceed 15%
grade
without it being paved
and
just going
off of the original drawings there,
it would be right at 15.
>> Right, I think it's 10 for pavement. You don't have, You can have a grade up to fifteen,
ten to 15 and it has to be paid, yeah. Yeah, yeah. Okay, well, so again,
>> yeah, I like the thought we'd have to go through it
And maybe,
Jim, you walk them through the
site plan special permit
checklist
and so you can see what kind of flags that might show up with them if they were to continue on and then
go to the wetlands and see what wetlands
would require
if you were to make an application.
In and then you can you can make the decision on whether or not
you'd want to move forward with the plan or not.
Can do that.
>> Well,
great. Thank you so much for listening to us and,
and,
you know, in contemplating this idea with us.
It's really
>> Thank you. Well, wish you the best of luck and I appreciate
your initiative
in trying to get
a plan developed
before the train leaves the station and we're running to catch up to it. Right.
That makes a lot of Thank you very much. Great, thank you.
Okay,
moving on to the next item
is
Mr. Devine still with us?
I think Amanda you have him on mute maybe?
I just unmuted him.
Okay. Thank you.
>> I'm
not sure whether I am muted or not. We I hear you.
Welcome.
>> I'm an old broadcaster and not being able to control my mic is a huge However,
first,
really would like to commend you, Mr. Chairman and the members of the commission
for your patience, your attention to detail
and your whole demeanor during this hour and hour and a half meeting.
You've been involved in a lot of town meetings in previous lives
and I know how tough it can be. Thank you for allowing me to chat a little bit about the project that I hope to put before you in time for your May meeting.
This house at Bearswamp Road is my wife and my tenth house.
It will be our fourth restoration of the historic home.
We left a wonderfully restored one in New Hampshire and specifically chose Andover for a couple of reasons. The obvious, you all know, you live here.
In addition addition to that, it provided us with enough land
to have a
detached accessory apartment
for our son.
Our son is a currently unemployed
Baltimore here. City.
He wants to get back to the land
and he's going to be our caretaker. You can tell by this space, right, that I'm going to need a caretaker before too many more years go by.
One of the contingencies,
in fact the contingency of buying our house in December
of last year was checking with zoning to make sure that the,
what we were calling at that time a caretaker cottage, would be permissible under the Andover zoning regulation.
Told in fact that it was
and Jim has confirmed that in some subsequent discussions.
As I've read the zoning regulations,
Section
4.11.3
does require a special permit
for a detached
accessory apartment.
As you all know, the special permit regulations are very, very detailed,
require a lot of time, effort and a pretty big expense to prepare
an application that completely follows that.
My reading of those seems to indicate that those regulations were written to cover any and all eventualities
which could be permitted
by a special permit.
In that initial run, the detached accessory apartment is not even mentioned.
The detached accessory apartment
references
those requirements for a special permit
under
Section 411.3
that we would be required to meet a number of items.
We can meet most of those items quite handily.
Requirements
by Section 4.11.2
that
can all be met. In fact, I've already done a checklist for myself and we meet all of those.
Architectural plans to be submitted,
those
are in progress.
They're being done by
Don Teranelli.
We should see our third and final set this week.
That brings me to Section 23.2b,
that's the site plan.
First, let me tell you that what we are proposing
is detached accessory apartment which satisfies
all of the other requirements including the maximum of 800 square feet,
which
includes the porch.
So we're really talking
a foundation
that is half the size of the meeting room that you folks would normally be meeting in.
That foundation is 20
feet by 30 feet and then the balance is a porch.
It seems like
a very, very minor improvement to a lot. We have 6.96
acres here at 84 Bearthorne Road.
We plan to locate the accessory apartment
well behind the road.
In fact, it's way over 200 feet,
it's about 300 feet off the road.
Its closest neighbor is 131
feet away
and that is to the east.
Our neighbor to the west is about two fifty feet away.
If you were to drive by the site and you look there was an old barn which at some point is going to get the divine restoration touch to it located
pretty much beside where we are proposing to build.
If I may, I'm going to call it a caretaker's cottage. I know that's not literally correct.
It's up here at the moment. That's where we want to build a caretaker's cottage.
It can hardly be seen from the road.
What
I am proposing and I do understand because Jim has made sure I understand
that the commission cannot issue a waiver without seeing the application. I understand that.
But
if I don't have a sense
that the commission is willing to entertain
the kind of site plan proposal that I would like to make,
partly because I can do 90% of it myself and partly because
it will save me a lot of time and partly because it will save me thousands of dollars.
What I am proposing
to do is to provide the Commission
with a site plan drawn on our A2 survey from 1985
which is on file with the town.
Adding to that the attachments
which would include
approval obviously for septic system and the driveway
and the other things that I know are required to do that.
That
would allow me again to demonstrate.
I know that Section 23.2
H,
you certainly can waive
most of the sections if not all of whatever pieces
of Section
23.2,
yes,
sections one,
sections four, five and six. Those are the site plan sections.
And
I guess I'm hoping
that I can find you open to accepting as complete an application which would include
site plan drawn on the A2 survey.
Jim,
and I thank him for this, has been out. He's seen my property.
He knows where we want to build. He saw it this past weekend.
He saw what appeared to be a little bit of a wetland
closer to my neighbor on the West Side,
which appears to be well away from the requirement that it be at least 100 feet away from any construction.
And I guess
at that point, I'm ready, willing and eager to have the Commission's guidance.
>> Okay. So
you
are going to be the first person
who has taken advantage
of our accessory apartment regulation that we
drafted a year or so ago.
And we
labored over those extensively
to try and
provide exactly what you're looking for,
but still put adequate controls into place so that we didn't have people building
two houses on single lots.
And I went
and reviewed
the articles
four, five, and six of what, 23.2,
I think.
And while there's a lot of stuff in there
that probably
is not
applicable to you.
There's a lot of stuff in there that I think we would like to see.
And I think 90%
is in what you were planning to do anyhow.
But what I would expect Jim to do with you on our special permit checklist
is to go through
each item on our checklist with you
and just verify that we've got a complete application.
And he
does have latitude to make recommendation
to the Commission on things that
you
think are not applicable and then it would come before the Commission to decide whether or not
we agree with that.
So I would not
I would prefer to not discuss
a complete waiver of
sections four, five, and six at this point, because I think there are some things in there that we would need to look at.
I absolutely agree with that. Just
>> so you know, the way I would do it is the application comes in,
I would go through
each of the items in section 4.11
of our regulations
see
if we
meet
the intent of that. And then I would go through
the
special permitting site plan thing to just see if there's anything else in there,
and then
we would go from there. But I would be intending
to do a pretty thorough review of each of the items in there just to convince myself
that yes, we needed it or no, we didn't because it is the first time we've gone down this path.
But your situation is exactly what we intended when we put that article in there.
And your size of a lot is exactly what we were looking at when we put the
article in there as well. So I think
the
likelihood of success is very high. I don't think it's very
hard.
But when we talk caretaker cottage, we view that more as another
house on the lot as opposed to putting a shed on the lot. We want to make sure that
the town is protected
in that nature.
Jim or any other
commission member have any other comments that you'd like to make on that?
>> I think that was pretty clear. It's the house, it's not a shed.
>> Yes. It
will be a
seven ninety
two square foot
building
which will include
22 by six foot covered porch and the covered porch needs to count towards the 800 total square feet of the property.
So in effect our son's
accessory apartment
will put him in approximately six
sixty square feet.
That sounds good.
>> It's an observation.
It
seems that throughout the regulations or at least a few places, it does suggest
that folks come forward with looking for preliminary feedback.
And
in this
particular case,
it wasn't clear whether waivers would be
discussed prior to the submission of application or not.
I don't think the regulations are particularly clear on that. If the Commission has
wanted to provide me some direction on that, I would be happy to
to
be more specific as to what I bring to the Commission.
>> My thought was, as I looked through this,
I did not know what waivers we might expect. It looks like,
and again, you know, there's a couple of things it talks about parking spots by
the cottage and that
kind of stuff.
But I would think that the next
step might be to come to us with a drawing
that has
what's there currently
and where he would
like to
put the
caretaker cottage.
And at that point, we might choose to even go out and do a site visit
to just make
sure that we don't see any other stumbling blocks to it. But right this minute, it looks like what he wants to do to me
is pretty straightforward.
>> Is
it going to be a separate well and septic?
>> It will be a separate
septic
and that's from a time standpoint that's my one concern right now. I made the application
last week. I'm
hopeful that it will be the test for the soil test will be scheduled in time for me to have my application completed and in Jim's hands at least
a week before
your May meeting.
The well, I did have a pressure test and a flow test done on our existing well and we will be using the the existing well to satisfy the water need for the
detached accessory apartment.
Right.
And like Jed was saying, there's parking requirements.
>> Oh, the parking requirement we have space already with our existing garage
for three or four cars and that's what the plan is our vehicles there.
I know I need to provide access
for an emergency vehicle and I will also need to provide access to that back part of our lot to do the construction.
So there actually are two pathways to do that.
I've already had
some work done to get rid of a mess between our garage and Bears Swamp Road.
Ron's landscaping came down and did some extensive cleaning out. Get rid of an old dog house and a bunch of rubber tires and even a tailgate from a pickup truck that had been thrown down.
That will take a little bit more grading and that will be a place to be able to drive the vehicle down behind the garage and then along the tree line on the grass.
I really don't have any
desire,
plan or perceived need
to do anything in terms of
permeated driveway or a
gravel driveway or anything like that. I don't think it's needed. It's a long walk back there,
but he's 51. He's 24 years young, 23 years younger than I. Yep. And I just
>> I went back and looked because I thought it was going to tell us that you needed two parking spots by the caretaker cottage,
but it does not. It says off street parking shall be provided for both dwellings, with at least two spaces for the principal dwelling
and one for the accessory apartment. Right. It sounds like what you're looking at there meets
our requirements.
>> Meet,
as best I have read everything,
we meet all of the requirements of 11.2
I think,
which is the base requirements and so forth. We meet everything for 4.11.2
already and what I really need to do, obviously, is provide you with a plan, site plan, that will allow you to do the due diligence that I know you need to do and that I applaud as a matter of fact.
>> Okay.
I don't have anything else on this
unless you have something else for us, Mr. Devine. I think it sounds like a good plan and
>> look forward to seeing it. Are there wetlands on the property?
Pardon? Wetlands on the property?
>> I I didn't think so. No. When Jim looked this past weekend,
there is a wet area,
that is probably,
I'm guessing,
a 100 and
well, the area to my stone wall is like a 130
181 feet. I'm I'm guessing it's in the ballpark of between a 125 and a 150
before you hit anything.
So Jim, would this need a wetlands review?
>> It would would fall outside the Upland Review area. I mean, that would have to be
determined,
but
no, I don't think we require wetlands.
Okay.
It's outside the Upland Review?
>> Yeah. Mike, I mean, I I guess,
I'm not gonna tell you whether was wetlands that I was looking at, there's
an intermittent water course
that follows the north side of the property.
It's
more than a 100 feet away than the proposed site.
Wetlands associated with that intermittent stream?
>> They seem to be confined. I mean, I'm guessing, you know,
like,
not a lot of wetlands will be confined to that stream area,
In my opinion.
Wetland soils.
Right.
I only looked at that just so
case came up this evening.
I know that Mr. DeMine has
a time frame.
And he's got a lot of, he's got to put a lot in. It's still a lot of work. We've got to do the soil test.
Have the engineering work done.
The Commission accepts
patients at the public hearing. Typically,
you know, there's there's time inherent in the process.
Right.
Yeah.
>> We're just trying to bring up everything that could possibly come up.
>> Yeah, and that's a that's a gray area on how do you determine whether it has to go to wetlands
when you think it's
well clear and
I'm not sure the best way
to handle that.
Did you look,
Jim, on the Crogg diagram to just see if anything was, they had any wetlands
in the area? I did not. Okay, that might be something you or Mr. Devine could do. If there's nothing there, I think it's pretty clear.
If there is something there, then it would take some
assessment to get a ruling for wetlands that
gets outside,
no application required. And I don't think that would be very hard or lengthy either.
>> They could do a site walk down there real quick.
>> Yep.
Now,
did I hear Mr. Devine say he has
submitted the application to us?
>> No, not yet. The only application
that I have out there is for the soil test
and I
can't do the site plan fully until I know that I have an approved site for the septic system and that will come about with soil test. I'm
hopeful that that will be in hand before
I have no idea how backed up Mr. King might be, but I'm hopeful that that can be done between now and sometime in the first week.
I plan to give him a call tomorrow to see where things stand.
Do have one other question,
if I might.
I was listening to you Mr. Chairman talking with the
previous discussion about timetables
and I want to make sure that
what I'm understanding in terms of timetables is correct. I know that at least under normal circumstances,
I would present the application, it would go through Jim,
it would come to the Zoning Commission and when it came to the Zoning Commission, if it were accepted as complete, it would be at that meeting that the public hearing would be scheduled,
which could be as early as the next zoning commission meeting.
If
that hearing is held and there's no problem,
then the commission, as I understand it, can can vote to issue the permit at that time. And then I know that there is, I believe, it's either a twenty or a thirty day delay before construction can begin.
If I'm right on that and I am able to have this in Jim's hands
with sufficient time before your May meeting to give everybody a chance to do at least a preliminary review,
Is all of that possible? That would allow me to start construction
in July and probably be done by early fall.
>> I do think the timeline you discussed
is accurate,
with the exception of after we make a ruling on it and it gets
the ruling gets published.
If there's a newspaper like the River East, it would be
noticed there,
current with
the coronavirus,
it's
noted in our website
action.
After it's noted, there would be, I think it's fifteen days, not thirty,
before
just to allow anybody to
raise an issue that they might have with it. So I think your timeline was correct with the exception of that last thirty days is really closer to
fifteen days.
And if we had a good complete application
on this project at the start of the next meeting, I think that's
all very doable.
>> Excellent.
Excellent. Thank you for your time, for your guidance.
You've made me feel really
like I can get this done between now and I'm shooting as Jim knows for the end of the first week in May,
but certainly by the second week in May to be done.
I got some good help from the town clerk's office who has sent me a digital copy of
the A2 map for here. And
I'm
going to go to town. I'm going to start.
I appreciate it. I appreciate your time,
attention, your willingness to work with me. You're
>> going to like what you see, I'm sure. Thank you. You. Thank you. Well, and I appreciate having the opportunity to work on it upfront as opposed to
late late in the process. So good luck to you, Mr. Devine.
Thank you.
Welcome
to town.
>> Moving on the next item on the agenda is the approval of the meeting minutes from March 26.
And hopefully everybody had a chance to read through the minutes before
we got here.
>> This is Leanne. I'll move to approve the minutes of March 26. I'll
second.
>> Thank you, Leanne. Thank you, Scott. Any discussion on the minutes?
>> I have two minor points.
I don't know if you want to include them or not.
The first one is on roll call.
I don't know if you want to indicate that Jerry Hardesty was seated
because he was an alternate.
That's item number two.
>> What do you think Linda? Is that
the best way to handle that?
Yeah, I can
>> do that. That's fine. Okay. Okay. And then the second item again, it could be considered minor. But
when you start off in item number one,
Anne
opened the meeting. And then
you were elected under 5A.
And you took over the meeting. I don't know if at that point it should be indicated that upon election,
you assumed the position of the chair for the meeting?
>> I
did have a similar comment where on roll call, it's got me as the chair and I wasn't the chair
at that point.
So I think your
comments,
a good one, Susan,
it should reflect that I was just a
member when we seated
and
that
under the election of officers
you can put that I assumed chair for the Commission.
I
have two items. Are we done with that?
Yep.
>> Under number six, administrative report from zoning agents.
If we could
the second sent second sentence says the gravel operation has been currently dormant.
I'd like to have that identified as the
operation at the Extramart.
Okay. And also,
>> Jim made a couple of remarks about that project.
Jim, if you could repeat them so that they're included.
I think I I thought I saw a version of it somewhere, but it's not in the one I'm looking at now. I know something some things were sent out as a revision.
Jim,
do you see what I mean?
No.
I do recall, Jim.
>> What what I had said was that the
first phase of the project
had been completed, which
essentially the
100 feet to the rear of the property, the first 100 feet from the river.
And that at that point,
operation, it was easier to turn vehicles, equipment around.
Okay. Some changes could be made.
Didn't you say I something about the
>> think I said that it was site was draining well.
But
I mean, I've taken a look at it after a few storms and it has has drained well. Oh, what I said was okay. What I said was that the
owner would
would
take a look at
redefining the
drainage along
the adjoining property
after
we now
move around, right?
Up until now or up until he finished that first phase,
he was just kind of
using the property
for travel, using the property near the,
where the proposed swale was,
which ultimately ended up as
a stone.
A berm.
Not as it's
more of a berm right now. And it had been originally there was some discussion about more of a
taking a literally taking a bulldozer
heavy equipment and and
picking the property back, picking
the grade back towards the extra mark.
I'm not sure I understand.
>> Okay, right now if you walk into the property along the right hand side there's there's a berm and that berm was was installed in lieu of.
Of
carving a a road,
taking heavy equipment and pitching grade back towards Extramart.
Mhmm. And and the reason the reason that was done is
it
was
trucks were going over that
that
area and eliminating
any any pitch that that was there. It just wouldn't hold up.
Hence the berm. And now they
said they would revisit,
especially about
regrading that area
back into
the site.
And that's for purposes of trucks going over it?
I'm sorry, Leanne. That's
for purposes of trucks going over it?
>> Well, what I'm trying to say is that
they
couldn't maintain that
pitch towards,
towards Extremart from the,
from the south side of the lot because of truck traffic.
They couldn't maintain the berm?
>> No, they couldn't maintain the the pitch
in lieu of the berm.
That's why they ended up with the berm.
The berm is on more towards the perimeter of the of the site.
And they would revisit that.
>> Doesn't it
show a dozer cut to the south end of the property next to the adjacent? Shows it right on the print, I've seen it. Shows up a dozer cut
to the south of the property. Yep,
that's right there. To the adjacent landowner's
property, 50 feet away, the cut, the angle, the water that comes off that property back towards the X Mark property.
Right. Clearly on the print, and it's never done in the field.
>> I mean, what was explained to me is this was what was agreed upon. The berm was agreed upon in lieu of that because of travel way, it was a travel way.
And but now at this point, they were going to
revisit that. But,
I mean, I've seen very little activity there in the last I've seen equipment moving, but haven't seen trucks leaving.
>> I
think when the
commission
put that on there they were worried about what was gonna happen
after the gravel operation.
Now there's gonna be, you know obviously something's gonna happen there and they wanted to make sure that any water that comes
after
whatever is being done there now is
mitigated and put pushed back towards
Extramart and not towards
the south adjacent landowner's property.
>> Right. And that's
what the owner indicated they would they would look at
doing at this point.
There hasn't been anything there going on. Right.
Last few months.
>> So Lee Ann, was the purpose of the conversation we just had because you wanted it included in his remarks in the minutes or just because you wanted clarification
so that you had a better understanding of what it was we were talking about?
>> Well, mainly I wanted to include it in the minutes of last month because I think he made a couple of remarks about
the drainage
and
just the general status of the activity.
But I think what he's just said now is in lightning too, so I'm not sure where that belongs. But I think
if that can be part of the record,
let me see, looking at my agenda.
If that can be part of if that can be kind of made part of his record for
this meeting that we're in right now,
if that's okay, I think that would be very helpful.
Both.
>> Is Linda.
What I could do is add it under zoning agent report.
>> Yep.
Yeah. Is that okay with everybody? Because I think that's what Jim just said, I think, elaborates on
a lot on what he said last month and also gives a report for this month, and so I think it does both. So if we could apply it to my original question about him repeating his remarks
for the minutes of last month.
And then also,
as I said, he's just expanded on it, if that can be included
for this meeting.
Okay.
>> Thank you. Who I wonder who decided on a berm
when
the print clearly showed
a cut
by a dozer?
>> My understanding it was a discussion between Chris Bell and John that I I don't know that for a fact.
I'm sorry Chris Bell and who?
John Valente.
Chris Bell being the engineer.
Yep.
>> I don't know why they would expect, you know, to be able to make a berm,
a hold up after, you know, trucks are driving over it. It's gonna knock it down. The berm is out of the way.
I'm sorry. Berm is you repeat that?
Go ahead.
>> Berm is not where
the dozer plate would have
Just to the right of that. Yeah. Where the dozer plate would have would have been
pitched the water back towards X-ray.
>> I'm sorry, Jim. Could you repeat one more time that your explanation about the difference between the berm and the alternative?
>> The berm is along
South of the property, so it's the right hand side of the property as you're looking in from Route 6.
And it's it's a raised berm.
And it was.
Apparently an alternative to.
Installing
is to running a bulldozer
along.
Along that perimeter just
inside of the berm as I understand it.
Berm is out. It's not in the same area. The berm's not getting
crashed by traffic.
No. It's remained pretty much intact.
Okay.
Okay, thanks.
>> Okay, so Linda, do you have
an idea of what Jim's initial comments were from last meeting that you can include in that section
and then put the rest of the discussion
in the zoning agent report for this month?
>> Yeah, I can actually probably go back and listen to the audio from this meeting and get his words. Okay. The amended minutes.
>> To me, it all sounded like one sort of big discussion.
So
I think we
talked about
>> Well, Linda, how about A portion and you have a second and you have amendments.
>> Yep. And
what were specific amendments that you have recorded there for us?
They have to do with
>> I guess you can go back in Yeah, I have to bring it down.
>> To make note that you took over the meeting as chair after you were elected. Yep. That Greg Hardisty was seated as the alternate.
Then Yep. Verbiage
regarding the gravel pit from last month. Okay. Very good.
So I don't know there's any
others.
>> So we've
got a motion, we've got a second, we've got a couple of modifications thereof.
Linda, do we need to make a motion for the amendments or can we do this one with just approved as amended?
>> You can approve them as amended. Okay. So we've got
>> the motion. We've got the second.
We'll take a vote.
Anne?
Aye.
Scott? Aye.
Leanne?
Aye.
>> Susan? Aye.
And I
as well.
The motion passes 500.
And so now we're moving on to the rest of the zoning agent report.
Jim.
>> Spring's here, fair amount of activity.
Couple of COs issued for new homes recently.
One by the lake and one one on Lakeside Drive and one on Skinner Hill Road.
Activity's a little slow because trying to work out who could sign off on wetlands permits right now, which was just the issue of the
bill or sign off on wetlands permit applications.
Projects,
not necessarily projects that go to the commission.
Other than that,
things are moving along as well as can be
given
tunnel closure and such.
That's all I have. Okay.
>> Well,
me thank you, Jim. I know you
have been
working very hard to get us
applications ready to go, and I appreciate
all your hard work on those.
Moving on to item nine, miscellaneous item.
I am not aware of any miscellaneous items. Does anybody else have any?
Hearing none, we'll move on to public speak. I'm not sure any of the public are
remaining.
But if there's a public person that wants to speak,
please speak.
Hearing none, we'll move on to
item 11, Commission open discussion.
Is
there anything that
any of the Commission members would like to discuss this evening?
>> This is Leanne. I have two quick things. Yep.
Excuse me. One is
for purposes of the record, should we acknowledge
Jerry Hardisty's resignation
between now and the last meeting?
Yes.
And so I think that you just did.
>> Okay. Just to put it on the record because I know I agree. Good
For
>> example, when George Knox resigned as an alternate,
I personally didn't know it. I had the impression that a couple of other members didn't know it. So just so that we know in what timeframe Jerry resigned.
>> Okay.
To comment on that, Leigh Ann,
I know the agenda for the last meeting started out with accepting the resignation of Bob Hamburger.
When
Amanda was going through and updating the names on our website, she asked me should I take George Knox off?
And I said, well, I don't know that he's resigned.
And
so I asked Amanda to leave his name on there for the time being.
I was hoping to twist his arm as we went out to the St. Patrick's Day seniors thing
that got canceled because of the
coronavirus.
I haven't had a chance to run into him yet to ask him
why he was resigning and whether or not he would reconsider.
So we have left George's name on our website for the time being. Amanda, did he
give a letter?
I
>> never saw the letter.
So that is why I was asking Jed. And I actually asked Carol. I'm waiting to hear back about George.
But
This usually
is Linda. Usually Carol sends out the letter.
>> Yeah. Scott, this is Linda. I believe one of the one of the last times I was in town hall, I went went and I did find the letter at the town clerk's office of his resignation.
Was it in the
commission
binder?
>> Was
ask Carol where she's where it is, but it's in the it's in the vault room. It's it's part of the record of his his resignation, I think as of January 1 or something.
Wow.
>> January 1. If in fact we find that there is a letter, we will accept it and then I'll go twist his arm. But
until we see a letter.
>> Follow-up with Carol and Carol did provide me with Susan England's
>> being sworn in. And he obviously has not come to any meetings so it's
kind
of like maybe he thinks he's resigned
but
anyhow
we'll look for the letter and act on the letter if one exists.
>> And along the same lines,
have we received I know the River East hasn't been publishing for two or three weeks or what have you, but have we received any responses to ads for other members?
>> Not that I am aware of.
And I would encourage each of us, I know I've approached a couple of guys
to ask them if they would like to be on the commission and I haven't gotten any takers yet.
Oh,
so I did run into
Bob Hamburger who was driving down the road, stopped to say hi the other day.
He is feeling
a little better,
struggling,
said that he was considering
if he could come back on as a regular member
after he gets back to battery. So there has been a little interest. I told Bob,
be happy to have his experience on the commission
if he were to choose to take that route.
That might happen.
Anybody else have any other open discussion items?
Hearing none, guess the last
open
item is just to thank each of you for
hanging in there
as
I got my first public hearing under my belt and
a rather
outdated
application
hopefully
done
without
messing up too many regulations there.
And Amanda, I really appreciate your support on getting
all the documents up.
I certainly could not have done that. So I appreciate
everybody's
help
in making tonight's meeting a success.
>> Thanks for stepping up Jed. I know everyone really appreciates it.
Yes, definitely.
Really Jed, thank you. Well I'm
>> sure there's one or two people out there that probably don't, but
there you go. Well, we'll do the best we can and that's all we can do.
Moving
>> I do just want to point out that all of the meeting documents will be uploaded to the town website.
>> Okay, and so that's what makes it part of the public record?
Those stay there forever?
>> You know, that's a good point. I think what we'll do with our new website is have an archive
of everything.
>> Yeah. And
I thought I saw something
on the
how to do virtual meetings
that suggested that once town hall is open again, we have to take all those records, and it almost alluded to we were required to maintain a paper copy in a file.
But I'll go back and take a look at that. But I think we
can have the public records online, but
it's always good to have that hard copy paper in the file cabinet for that.
Okay, moving on to adjournment.
Nobody wants to adjourn?
I'll move to adjourn at 09:31,
Ms. Leanne.
>> Okay,
second?
Who is the second? Ann.
Ann. Thank
you. Thank you all very much. Meeting's adjourned at 09:31.
Good night, everyone. Good
Leanne,
I don't know